So, we are starting today on י"ג עמוד ב'. Yud Gimmel Amud
Bais.
We pick up, we're a little behind, today's דף daf is י"ד,
Yud Daled, י"ד, Yud Daled, but we start with י"ג עמוד ב'.
Yud Gimmel Amud Bais. We pick up where it says מיתיבי, Mesivay,
beginning of a line that's about two-fifths of the way down across
from the תוספות Tosafos that says כ"מ ד'. Chaf Mem Daled. So
we had been discussing the fact that non-Jewish ownership exempts somebody from
the מצוה mitzvah of בכור, bechor, like we had said in the
first פרק, perek, now we're saying it by the בכור bechor of
sheep and goats and cows. And we were talking about how הלכה
halachically a non-Jew acquires from a Jew and we have a whole
big ברייתא braisa that emphasized it was through כסף, kesef, through the
exchange of money, but then we had the position of אמימר Amemar
that said, excuse me, yes, of אמימר Amemar who said that it's
through משיכה, meshicha, through taking possession of the object. And that becomes
a very important practical issue. Now we wrap this up with the
following: מיתיבי, Mesivay, I'll ask you. הלוקח
גרוטאות מן העובדי כוכבים, Halokeach grutaos min ha'ovdei kochavim, this is a
משנה mishna in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and we learned this when
we learned עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, almost the same discussion. If somebody
buys raw metal, like you know, sort of trash metal from the
non-Jew, because you know, you're in that's your business, you deal with
scrap metal. Okay, however, of course there's going to be a problem
which is, as you might imagine, amongst that scrap metal is you
find an idol. So what is the story? ומצא בהן עבודת כוכבים,
Umatza bahen avodas kochavim, you find amongst the scrap metal an idol.
אם עד שלא נתן מעות משך, Im ad shelo nasan maos mashach,
if you took possession, that's משיכה, meshicha, you drew it near you
before you gave the money, יחזיר, yachzir, then you can return it
because presumably you did not yet own it and therefore you can
back out on the deal. אם משנתן מעות משך, Im mishenasan maos
mashach, if however you owned it and therefore you took possession after
you've given the money, if you took possession of it after you've
given the money, then יוליכם לים המלח, yolichen l'yam hamelach, then you
already own it and therefore you can't benefit from it, so what
do you do? You go ahead and you take the value and
you throw it into the into the Dead Sea.
Now, why exactly it helps by throwing it into the sea is
a different issue, but that's not, of course,
yes, but it doesn't actually say you throw the object, it says
you throw the value of it, הנאה לים המלח. hana'ah l'yam hamelach.
So anyway, I'm not going to talk about it, that's not exactly
our issue, right? Obviously the more simple thing to do would be
to say that you throw the thing itself out, but anyway, so
but that's not our issue. Our issue is when did you take
possession of it? And here it seems like the beginning says that
you took possession, meaning when does the ownership transfer? So the beginning
said you took possession, you did משיכה, meshicha, you drew it near
to you without giving money, so that was not enough. The end
said if you took possession after you gave money. So it sounds
like what affects the transaction is the combination of the two, the
giving of the money and the taking of possession, which is not
work according to either approach we said before, which was one approach
said that either the giving of the money, the other approach said
the taking of possession, here we have, here it sounded like both.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with it. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: ואי אמרת מעות קונות, Ve'im amarta maos
konos, if you say according to our approach, I don't know if
that's working or not, I might have, if you say according to
our approach that מעות maos is what affects the transaction, which is
what we were saying for most of yesterday, so
משיכה למה לי? meshicha lama li? Why does it say that you
have to, why does the end say
if you took possession after you gave money? Why did you need
to take possession at all? Why did you need to do משיכה?
meshicha? So the גמרא Gemara says: הכא במאי עסקינן שקיבל עליו לדון
דיני ישראל. Hacha bemai askinan shekibel alav l'dun dinei Yisrael. No, you
made a stipulated that the way the transaction would be affected would
be the way it works with Jews, which is by משיכה. meshicha.
And therefore that's why the end it mentions doing משיכה. meshicha. The
problem is the beginning says if you did משיכה meshicha without giving
money, it did not take effect. So you cannot say that משיכה
meshicha is what matters. If you just compare, the beginning says you
did משיכה meshicha without money, didn't take effect. The end says you
did משיכה meshicha with money. So the obvious, the only way to
interpret it, thank you, is that you need both משיכה meshicha and
money. Any one of them does not work with this משנה. mishna.
So the גמרא Gemara is trying to say that משיכה meshicha works,
that's what's going on at the end, and you stipulated that you
would do it like you do it with Jews, you do it
with משיכה. meshicha. גמרא Gemara says one minute, אי הכי, ee hachi,
if that's true, מעות למה לי? maos lama li? Why does it
say that you did משיכה meshicha after you gave money? Who needed
the money?
So the גמרא Gemara says: הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, this is what
it means: אף על פי שנתן מעות, Af al pi shenasan maos,
even if you've given the money, אם משך אין אי לא משך
לא. im mashach in, ee lo mashach lo. The only, you only,
the transaction only takes effect when you do משיכה. meshicha. So now
because the end of this mentioned משיכה, meshicha, we're trying to say
all that matters or you stipulated that all that matters is משיכה.
meshicha. Then the problem is, so what about the beginning? The beginning
you also did משיכה, meshicha, it says that you're allowed to back
up. So the גמרא Gemara says: אי הכי קשיא רישא, ee hachi
kashya reisha, what do you do with the רישא reisha of it?
So אמר אביי: amar Abaye: רישא משום דהוי מקח טעות. reisha mishum
dehavei mekach taus. In the end, you're right, in both the beginning
and the end, you've done משיכה, meshicha, you've taken possession of this
scrap metal, again for those just coming, the case is that you
took scrap metal, you bought scrap metal from a non-Jew, there was
an idol in it, are you allowed to back out or not?
Now what it is is that the simple sense of this משנה
Mishnah says if you've just done משיכה meshicha you can back out
of it. If you've done משיכה, meshicha, taken physical possession, and giving
the money, you cannot back out. But this doesn't fit with the
גמרא Gemara that assumes that it's either one or the other, not
both. So now we're trying to read that the whole thing is
that you did משיכה. meshicha. So why can you back out at
the beginning and not back out at the end? So אביי Abaye
says, "Oh, because the beginning it was a מקח טעות." mekach taos.
It really, even though you did take possession, you can reverse the
sale because it was in error. You never were expecting there to
be idols in the scrap metal. So that's why you're allowed to
reverse the sale. Of course, if that's true, the same is true
of the end, right? So what's the difference? The only difference in
this משנה Mishnah because the beginning and the end is whether you've
given money or not. So how can you say that it's about
being a מקח טעות? mekach taos? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said back
to
him, רישא משום דאיכא מקח טעות סיפא ליכא מקח טעות? reisha mishum
d'ika mekach taos seifa leika mekach taos? What? There's a mistake in
purchase in the beginning and not at the end? In both cases
it was a purchase in error. So why again are you allowed
to back out in the beginning and not the end? אלא אמר
רבא, ella amar Rava, rather says רבא, Rava, רישא וסיפא מקח טעות.
reisha v'seifa mekach taos. They both really are a purchase in error.
רישא דלא יהיב זוזי, reisha d'lo yahiv zuzei, now here's the only
difference. Really clear, the only difference between the beginning of the משנה
Mishnah and the end of the משנה Mishnah is that in the
beginning when you can back out, you haven't paid your money. In
the end when you can't back out, you have paid your money.
The simple sense of that is is that to take for the
transaction to take effect, you need both: giving money and taking physical
possession. But again, that doesn't work in either model the גמרא Gemara
has. The גמרא Gemara says it's possible money, it's possible taking physical
possession, משיכה, meshicha, it never suggests that you need both. So what
are we going to do with this משנה? Mishnah? So now what
רבא Rava is saying is you're right. It's a case where משיכה
meshicha works, either that's the law that משיכה meshicha works for non-Jews
or you stipulated that. And it is true that the only difference
is giving money. And here's the story: even though you have taken
possession, the transaction did take effect, you're allowed to back out because
it's a מקח טעות. mekach taos. That's the רישא. reisha. That's the
beginning of it. Because, you know, you never expected there to be
idols. Right, it was unintended, you would never have bought it if
you'd known there were idols in it. So then, okay, so in
the end you should also be allowed to. But here's the problem.
It's really an appearances problem. It's not a halachic problem, or it's
halachic because of an appearances problem, which is that if you've already
given the money and now you want to reverse the sale, what
are you going to do? You're going to give him back the
whole thing and the idols, you know, you gave me this lousy
idol. You're going to give him back the whole thing and he's
going to give you back the money. So now it's going to
look like you are like you are selling your idol and getting
money for it. That's the problem. But really what affects the sale
is the act of משיכה. meshicha. Okay, so he says like this:
רישא דלא יהיב זוזי לא מחזי כעבודת כוכבים ביד ישראל. reisha d'lo
yahiv zuzei lo mechezi k'avodas kochavim b'yad Yisrael. In the beginning you
haven't given the money. First of all, it doesn't ever look like
you really took full possession of it, although halachically you did. Since
you never paid for it, it doesn't look like you took full
possession. And when you reverse, it just looks like you're backing out.
סיפא דיהיב זוזי, seifa d'yahiv zuzei, in the end where you paid
for it already, so מחזי כעבודת כוכבים ביד ישראל. mechezi k'avodas kochavim
b'yad Yisrael. It seems like when you take possession, it's more it
more appears that you really do own it. And when you give
it back, it more appears like you're selling it. So therefore that's
the problem. But yet the beginning and the end, really what effects
the transaction is משיכה.
meshicha. But I don't understand it. I mean, either way you still
have this עבודת כוכבים avodas kochavim and you're getting your money back.
So someone's still going to see you give this idol back in
the first case
to the עבודת כוכבים, avodas kochavim, so it still looks like you're
giving idols
into...
Apparently, apparently it's different because if they saw you didn't pay it,
they'll understand that you never took possession, you realized it was an
idol and you backed out of it.
What if they paid you before?
Alright, there's a general
assumption here that people are aware of what goes on, okay? You're
right, you have to assume that in every case. Alright, anyway, let's
keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara says like...
Yeah, I have a question, I'm sorry.
This implies a public marketplace. Think about it.
That's sort of what Michael said.
People are aware, there has to be people there, there has to
be commerce going on. But if this occurs in a place that's
a field somewhere and
there's no people, who knows? Right, so that's what Michael said. So
yeah, it does assume that or it assumes that, you know, that
that's enough of a rule. Look, in principle, we're just being strict
on you. In principle, you would be allowed to back out in
both cases because it's a מקח טעות. mekach taos. So the point
is we're going to be strict about cases that are more likely
to be led to misinterpretation. We're not saying it'll always lead to
misinterpretation, but there's a greater likelihood it'll lead to misinterpretation.
Well, why can't someone stand and say, "I did not allow, I
did not intend to purchase an idol"?
Alright, because the general rule is that the Rabbis don't allow, you
know, want to make, you know, as any legal system, you want
to have regular rules. You don't want everything to be based on
context. If you demand that somebody does that, it's not always going
to happen. You want basic regular rules for people to follow. That's
the bit... yeah, exactly. That's the bit... you can't have a legal
system because, "Well, I'm going to make do this, so then therefore
it won't apply in my case."
Okay, so let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. Alright,
ואביי אמר ליה להכא, v'Abaye amar lei l'hacha, here's אביי's Abaye explanation
of the difference. Definitely the difference in the beginning and the end
is whether you gave money. For רבא Rava it's how much it
looks like you actually took possession or how much it looks like
you're selling it back when you get money back. אביי Abaye says
here's the difference about giving money: רישא מקח טעות דלא ידע דלא
יהיב ליה זוזי. reisha mekach taos d'lo yadei d'lo yahiv lei zuzei.
The beginning it's a mistake in purchase because he didn't know that
he didn't give him money. because look, you got something you didn't
expect, you didn't give money for it, and therefore it was an
error. Now the—and—it was also an error, but here's the difference. סיפא
Seifa at the end לאו מקח טעות, lav mekach taut, so it's
not a—a mistaken sale, sale in error, why? It certainly seems like
it. דכיון דיהיב זוזי, de-keivan de-yahiv zuzei, once you've already paid, כי
קמשיך איבעי ליה לעיוני והדר למשוך, ki kamashich ibaei lei leyunei ve-hadar
limshoch, then before you take possession you have a greater responsibility to
investigate what it is that you're actually taking. So what he says
is like this, it's actually quite interesting. Although halakhically you own it
once you bring the object into your possession, once you physically take
possession, that effects the transaction. But psychologically, if you haven't given money,
you could say, look, I didn't pay out the money yet, I
didn't get around yet to checking it out, so therefore it was
a total surprise to me and therefore I didn't expect this, I
brought it back out of it. Now, and it's a מקח טעות.
mekach taut. But once you've given the money, interesting, the giving of
the money doesn't effect the change of ownership, but if you've already
paid out the money, then before you do the act of משיכה
meshicha to take possession of it, then you'd better—then you have a
responsibility, you'd better make sure this is what you want, okay? Because
you know you're already out the money and therefore, and therefore that
creates a greater sense of, you know, of your responsibility to double
check, and if you're not being careful, then it's your own fault
and you've assumed the risk.
And that's the expression caveat emptor, let the buyer beware.
Now interestingly, you would say that such a—that such a nice idea,
would that be true in any הלכה, halacha, that the difference about
מקח טעות mekach taut or not would be affected by whether or
not you've paid out the money already, that that switches the sense
of whose responsibility it is, who's the buyer beware to check out?
So if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says like this,
where's the
תוספות? Tosafot? Yeah, דכיון דיהיב זוזי
איבעי ליה לעיוני והדר למשוך.
de-keivan de-yahiv zuzei
ibaei lei leyunei ve-hadar limshoch. תוספות Tosafot says, ואף על גב דבשאר
מקח טעות לא אמרינן הכי. ve-af al gav de-bishar mekach taut lo
amrinan hachi. We don't say this rule in normal cases of sale.
Normally, if a sale is in error, you can't say, oh, you
gave the money already, you should have checked it out. שאני לוקח
מעובד כוכבים דאיבעי ליה לאסוקי דעתיה טפי שמא יש בו עבודת כוכבים.
shani lokeach me-oved kochavim de-ibaei lei le-asukei daatei tefei shema yesh bo
avodat kochavim. Here it is more likely and therefore, you know, you
have a great—since it's more—it more could be anticipated, therefore once you
give the money, you assume the risk. Now of course, at a
certain point, if it really was anticipated, you can't say מקח טעות,
mekach taut, right? If a certain percentage of things have this problem,
you can't say, oh, I wasn't expecting it, מקח טעות. mekach taut.
You know, it's a certain percentage and you—you know that that's the
risk that you're assuming when you buy it. So what תוספות Tosafot
is doing is he's trying to bring this very close. It's very
close to the level where the normal frequency of the likelihood of
it would already make it a non-מקח טעות mekach taut because you
should have expected it was likely. And the only thing that's tipping
the scales is once you give the money, then that becomes your
responsibility. So in theory, you could translate this to other cases, but
it's only cases where already the likelihood that this would be a
scenario—that this would be the case—would already be pretty high. And if
it's high enough, then you don't need to give the money, then
it's not a מקח טעות mekach taut anyway because that's just part
of the assumed risk.
Yes, or you're in a weird marketplace. If you go to a
metal place in one area that deals with, you know, like certain
products, let's say bricks, you're not likely to get—but metal might be—exactly.
So it has to do with the exact scenario, right? And are
you dealing—are you going to—are you going to buy your scrap metal
from a used—from a used car lot, you know, from where they—a
car junkyard, or are you going from a used—scrap metal from somebody
that collects it from people's homes, you know? Different scenarios, right? Different
scenarios would lead to different issues.
Okay, right, we're in the marketplace.
Exactly. Okay, so anyway, that's what we did. We read this so
that the money—you didn't need both money and משיכה, meshicha, you just
need משיכה. meshicha. The money determines whether or not number one there's
a rabbinic problem that it looks like you're buying and selling an
idol, or whether it changes the degree of responsibility so that you
can no longer claim מקח טעות. mekach taut. Let's finish this
up. We have רב אשי Rav Ashi אמר. amar. רב אשי Rav
Ashi says, מידי דרישא משיכה אינה קונה סיפא נמי משיכה אינה קונה.
midi de-reisha meshicha eina kona seifa nami meshicha eina kona. No, you're
misreading this whole ברייתא. braita. The emphasis, the basic difference between the
beginning and the end—the משנה mishna rather—the beginning and the end is
whether you've given money. משיכה meshicha does not do the possession. It
doesn't work—in the beginning you didn't take possession because you did משיכה
meshicha because you were allowed to back out. The סיפא seifa also
you didn't take possession. Okay, so therefore now, ואיידי דתנא רישא משך
תנא נמי סיפא משך. ve-aidi de-tana reisha mashach tana nami seifa mashach.
That's probably the easiest answer. He said the beginning said if you
did משיכה meshicha without paying the money, you have not taken—you're allowed
to back out. The end said, oh, but if you did משיכה
meshicha after paying the money, you're allowed to back out—I mean, you're
not allowed to back out. So what's the difference? Whether you paid
the money. So he said that's what's going on. משיכה meshicha is
irrelevant. It's like we always learned that money is what effects the
transaction with non-Jews. So why—and that's why in the end when you
gave the money you can't back out. Why did it say if
you gave the money and did משיכה? meshicha? It's because we were
talking about משיכה meshicha in the beginning, but really משיכה meshicha is
completely irrelevant. Really what's important here is did you give the money,
did you not give the money, that's what effects the
transaction. That's what—that's what רב אשי Rav Ashi says. Very simple read
of the משנה. mishna.
And it goes down to the מחלוקת machloket עובד כוכבים oved kochavim
how it works.
Yeah, but that's what we're going like—we're going like we said all
of yesterday. I mean, yes, it's not like a מימרא, meimra, but
it's like that major... ברייתא baraita *braita* that we had yesterday that
said that it's money. Okay, so according to you, you have two
major tannaitic sources that say that it's money. We'll talk about the
הלכה halacha. *halacha* in the end. The others are saying, well no,
even the others didn't disagree. They said you stipulated you would do
it with בדיני ישראל *b'dinei Yisrael*, you'd do it with משיכה meshicha
*meshicha*. So the simple set until now has been that על פי
דין *al pi din* everybody agrees that it's money. We'll talk about
the הלכה *halacha* in a minute. רבינא אמר מדסיפא משיכה meshicha. קנה
רישא נמי משיכה meshicha. קנה *Ravina amar mi'deseifa meshicha kana reisha nami
meshicha kana*. Since in the end it's about משיכה meshicha *meshicha* because
it says your משיכה *meshicha* and money, although it also mentioned money,
the beginning it's also about משיכה *meshicha*. Okay, so we're back to
the question, what difference does it make beginning or the end? The
רישא הכי קאמר *reisha hachi ka'amar*, but we're going to re-read the
beginning. The beginning says אם לא נתן ולא משך יחזור *im lo
natan v'lo mashach yachzor*, יחזיר
*yachzir*, it should be יחזיר *yachzir*, or יחזור *yachzor*, anyway. So here
we're reading it the following, we're reading, it sounds like we're changing
the text of the ברייתא *braita*, as opposed to the way we
had it, which was the beginning was משיכה *meshicha* back out, the
end was משיכה *meshicha* and money don't back out. He's saying no,
no, no. The end is neither משיכה *meshicha* nor money you can
back out. The end was משיכה *meshicha*, you money but not משיכה
*meshicha* you can't back out. Okay, so let's take a look. So
מאי יחזיר *mai yachzir*? יחזיר בדברים *yachzir bidvarim*. You can back out
with, you can back out from your, so what backing out is
there if you didn't give money or take possession? What type of
backing out is it? Nothing took effect. No, you can back out
from your commitment. You said you were going to buy it. קסבר
kasavar *Kasavar*, he's, this תנא *tanna* is of the opinion, גם יש
בהם משום מחוסרי אמנה *gam yesh bahem mishum mechusrei amana*. When you
say you're going to do something, this is a nice phrase, Bobby,
you'll like this phrase, words have in them lack of faith. Meaning
even if you just said something and you don't keep it, that's
considered like a breaking of faith. Okay, a breaking of an oral
contract if you would. And therefore you are not as a, you
know, you can't bring somebody to court and make them pay you
if they backed out on an oral commitment, but it is something
that is considered like a violation, something that you are not supposed
to do once you say you're going to do something. So therefore,
normally if I said to a, to you, I would buy something
from you, even though it doesn't take effect and I'm allowed to
back out, there's a sense that I've broken faith with you if
I back out. והני מילי ישראל מישראל *V'hani milei Yisrael mi'Yisrael*. That
a Jew between a Jew. Now it gets back into some of
the problematics we mentioned yesterday about issues relating to non-Jews. But here
what at least is, here what at least is worth noting here
is whether you agree with this, certainly, okay,
whether this actually was the historical facts at that time, what we're
about to read is certainly a question about reflecting their perception of
the non-Jews and the relationship of Jews and non-Jews. Meaning whether you
look at these things as when the attitudes against towards non-Jews as
purely just like, you know, sort of, what's the word I'm looking
for?
Anyway, discrimination, or whether there, look, we are, they're talking about Jews
who lived amongst an oppressive non-Jewish government and whether to some degree
there's a reflection of that reality. So let's read the next statement.
Okay, והני מילי ישראל מישראל דקיימי בדיבורייהו *v'hani milei Yisrael mi'Yisrael d'kaimi
b'diburaihu*, that they keep their word between each other. אבל Aval, ישראל
מעובד כוכבים דאינהו לא קיימי בדיבורייהו *Aval Yisrael mi'akum d'inu lo kaimi
b'diburaihu*, but when we're dealing with Jewish non-Jewish relations, this is, Bobby,
I am not saying this about today, I'm saying this about 2,000
years ago when the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* was being written, okay, and
this was their perception, okay, again whether it was the factual realities,
but it certainly was their perception, that said between us and them,
they don't keep their word to us, we don't have a responsibility
to keep our word to them. Lo. So that's what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says. Okay, Bobby, you'll have your say in a minute.
I am not defending this, I'm just translating here. Anyway, anyway, but
it is important to appreciate the historical context. Let's face it, Jews
have been like oppressed and martyred by non-Jews throughout the rabbinic period.
Anyway, the point is, if you, the way he's reading the ברייתא
*braita* is that if you had just not given money, not taken
possession, you're allowed to back out because it's Jew non-Jew, not Jew
Jew. However, once you actually give the money, then you're not allowed
to back out. So again, what's over, to just wrap up and
then we'll give Bobby her, her per se here, but to wrap
up the, the point, the point is that overwhelmingly the dominant theme
has been that what effects transaction between Jew and non-Jew is the
giving of the money, not the physical taking possession. We've only had
really a מימרא *memra* as a contrary voice. Even in this last
משנה mishna, *mishna* where it spoke about money and משיכה *meshicha* and
we had different ways of reading it, when it suggested to read
it that it was the act of משיכה *meshicha* that was significant,
that was when you stipulated that it would work as it works
with Jews. But overwhelmingly the dominant theme here is that what's the
basic way it works taking possession from non-Jews and vice versa is
through the giving of the money. That's what effects the transaction. Now
that's a very important question because it means that all הלכות halachos
*halachot* that deal with selling things to non-Jews in which that is
critical, like for example the חמץ chametz *chametz*, ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*
for שמיטה *Shmita*, and for בכור bechor, *bechor*, how do you do
it? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* rules like what is the dominant theme
of this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you do it through, through giving of
money. That's what effects the transaction. תוספות *Tosafot* says this whole גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* aside, since in general we rule like רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* who says that by ישראל *Yisrael* the עיקר הדין
*ikkar hadin* money works and it's the rabbi. but since fundamentally money
is what works by ישראל until they switched it, therefore the opposite
is what works by a non-Jew. משיכה works by a non-Jew, and
most ראשונים Rishonim rule that way against our entire גמרא, Gemara that
what works selling to a non-Jew is משיכה. Therefore they say by
all of these things you do it by משיכה. That's the עיקר
דין, ikkar din, although להלכה l'halacha we try to do both, both
having them take possession and giving them the money. And there's another
option which is also, then there's a question does חליפין chalipin work,
some type of a handkerchief, maybe that does work, doesn't work. And
then there's a question about how about having them take possession because
it's in their property, on their property, and therefore everybody agrees that
you can sell land to a non-Jew through money. So what you
do is you rent the land that the animal is on or
the חמץ chametz is on or whatever, you rent it for a
dollar, he gives you the money, everybody agrees that will be the
effects the transaction and the rental of the land. And then because
the animal or the חמץ or whatever is on his land, therefore
he takes possession because it's on his land. Anyway, this leads to
an enormously large literature on how to effect these transactions because of
all these הלכות halachos, where this issue about selling it to a
non-Jew has particular ritual significance, not just monetary significance. Bobby, you would
like to say?
I think everybody knows exactly what I'm about to say.
Go ahead and say it, it needs to be said.
And that is when when you we represent a nation of priests,
supposedly. So that means we represent השם. Hashem. And that means when
we give our word, right,
it should be our word.
Right. And as a reputation for a people, our word should be
our bond. And the fact that we have a double standard, my
mother used to say to me, I don't care what the neighbor's
kid can do. That doesn't make it right for you even if
she did it to you. You cannot go and do that to
her. And you know what, my mother was right, and I think
I really I would like to think if I lived in those
days I wouldn't feel any differently than I do today.
Right. Right, I think that's very legitimate. I will mention that we're
about to read the פרשה parsha of
ויצא Vayetzei where it's all about יעקב Yaakov and לבן Lavan and
you know and how do you deal with somebody that themselves is
not keeping and duplicity and not keeping to the standard you would
like to keep, and how do you do it so that you
know how do you on the one hand keep your integrity and
the other hand not be taken advantage of? Exactly. And I don't
think that there's a simple answer to that question, but you know
but I very much appreciate what you say and I just and
again I'll just reflect back that the גמרא Gemara you know at
least here the גמרא Gemara articulated it by at least by tucking
that this is their understanding about how they act to us. It's
not just a question of general just discrimination you know because they're
lesser than us. It's coming through a perspective that you know about
about the type of reciprocity and reactive and so on. But the
question is that you know the questions you raise are very important.
I will end by just sharing a joke that I love because
it's all about selling the ear of the animal to the non-Jew
to get out of it, which is you know about a an
Orthodox, Conservative, and Reform rabbi all get together and decide there's one
thing we can all agree on. So they all decide okay you
know what we can agree on we can agree on that smoking
should be forbidden because you know it's bad for your health and
it's bad for the environment and smoking is אסור. assur. Okay and
then so they all agree on that. Then a few months later
they all bump into each other on the street and they're all
smoking. So I heard this joke from an Israeli where everybody smokes
there you know anyway. So they're all smoking, particularly the Orthodox rabbi
anyway. So so they all look at each other what about what
we agreed on? So they look at the Reform rabbi and he
said said you know don't look at me like I believe that
the decisions of our committee had a vote but not a veto.
So then they look then they look at the Conservative rabbi and
he says yes it's true but if you look at the historical
record about the notes of the committee you'll find that there were
different versions of exactly how we came to the conclusion. They look
at the Orthodox rabbi and said what about you? He says don't
look at me, I sold my lungs to a גוי. goy.
So there you go. All right. Yes. That's exactly this הלכה.
So
are you saying everyone agreed that for a non-Jew money is okay
for land? Yeah.
Yeah, that's the overwhelming yes position. Yeah.
So what about so but you're saying that a lot of people
the predominant consensus is rule against this גמרא Gemara. because there's so
many other גמרות? Gemaras?
Because the גמרא Gemara. is about רבי יוחנן that says that it's
כסף kesef by a Jew and
therefore משיכה by a non-Jew.
No I know but so what about all the stuff we just
did?
Yeah. The גמרא Gemara itself acknowledged at the beginning that there's the
position of אביי. Abaye. This was all just working within the opposite
position. Okay, so the question is how much you take an entire
דף daf that assumes כסף kesef to be within you know to
be theoretical or how much you take it להלכה. l'halacha. רש״י Rashi
takes it להלכה, l'halacha, but most ראשונים Rishonim take it as theoretical.
Okay, now we move on. Top of יד עמוד א׳, yud daled
amud aleph, we begin the next דף. daf. כל הקדשים, Kol hakodashim,
now you might remember this משנה, Mishna, we had it exactly in
חולין, Chullin, it was not really analyzed there, we're going to have
it in תמורה Temurah because it deals with a lot of הלכות,
halachos we will deal with it here in בכורות. Bechoros. Let's take
a look. כל הקדשים שקדמו מום קבוע להקדשן, Kol hakodashim shekadmu mum
kavua l'hekdeshan, all sacrifices that the animal had a fixed blemish, a
blemish that was not transitory, and it preceded them being sanctified. So
you take your nice looking sheep, though with its broken leg or
some type of a blemish that isn't going away, and you say
this is an עולה. Olah. Okay, now it can't be an עולה
Olah because it has a מום. Mum. Now because the מום Mum
preceded your sanctifying of it, it never got sanctity of making it
fit for the altar. Okay, if you sanctified it and then it
got the blemish, its original sanctity was fit for the altar, now
it just can't be brought, but it doesn't lose that original sanctity
of being fit of of קדושת מזבח, Kedushas Mizbeach, sanctity for the
altar. Here, it was never fit from the moment you sanctified it,
and therefore it was an attempt to give it קדושת מזבח, Kedushas
Mizbeach, altar sanctity, but you only effected in giving it value sanctity,
קדושת דמים, Kedushas Damim, which means though, it doesn't mean even there
exactly קדושת דמים, Kedushas Damim, because what you are going to do
is, you're not just going to to
sell it and use the money to let's say, you know, to
go to the temple upkeep. You're going to sell it and use
the money to buy a קרבן. Korban. So it still is קדושה
Kedusha that eventually has to find its way to a קרבן, Korban,
but within this animal it was only for the outset to be
sold. And therefore, it's not real קדושת מזבח Kedushas Mizbeach in this
animal. Again, although not to be confused like with real קדושת דמים
Kedushas Damim where the value goes to the upkeep of the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so the fixed blemish was there beforehand. ויפדו,
Veyipadu, and then you redeemed it, which is what you have to
do with this anyway because it had a fixed blemish. So, the
question is, what is its status for a lot of things starting
with the firstborn? חייבין בבכורה, Chayavin Bebechora, it's obligated in the firstborn.
Now we haven't actually said this in a משנה, Mishna but if
something is הקדש, Hekdesh, it's exempt from firstborn. If I have a
קרבן Korban and it gives birth to a firstborn, it's exempt from
firstborn. Not only that, if I have a קרבן Korban that got
a blemish and I redeem it, people might remember פסולי מוקדשין, Psulei
Mukdashin, they have a residual קדושה Kedusha status. The תורה Torah says,
right, what should you do? It says, it says כצבי וכאיל, Katzvi
Vechayal, you can שחט Shecht it, you can eat it, but חז"ל
Chazal understand תזבח ולא גיזה ואכלת ולא ולא Tizbach Velo Giza Veachalta
Velo Velo what is it ולא עבודה, Velo Avoda, תזבח ולא עבודה
ואכלת ולא Tizbach Velo Avoda Veachalta Velo anyway גיזה Giza
anyway you cannot shear it, you cannot work it, okay, and even
after you've redeemed something that was once a קרבן Korban that had
a blemish, it has a residual קדושה Kedusha status. That is not
true by this. This which started with a blemish and then was
redeemed, it has no residual status, the entire קדושה Kedusha is removed
because it never had קדושה Kedusha that was fit for the altar.
Okay, so therefore, if I sanctified a קרבן, Korban, got a blemish,
removed it, and therefore that is still exempt from firstborn even now
that it's been removed because there's a residual status. If it started
with a blemish, I sanctified it and removed it, therefore it's fully
removed the קדושה Kedusha because it never was fit for the altar,
no residual status, now if it has a firstborn I am obligated
in the firstborn. So I'm obligated in the firstborn because it is
totally back to being not sanctified. חייבין בבכורה ובמתנות, Chayavin Bebechora Uvematanos,
I give the זרוע לחיים וקיבה, Zroa Lechayayim Vekeiva, right, the arm
and the jaw and the stomach, as we mentioned, this was why
we mentioned it in חולין, Chullin, also would not apply to any
animal with even residual קדושה, Kedusha, but this animal has no residual
קדושה. Kedusha. ויוצאין לחולין Veyotzin Lechullin are completely desacralized, ליגזז וליעבד, Ligazez
Veliaveid,
to be sheared and worked. This is the point I said, this
really proves as opposed to a sacrifice that's redeemed, has some residual
status, this has no residual status, once it's redeemed, go ahead, shear
it, work it, you know, do whatever you want. ולדן וחלבן מותר,
Veladan Vechalavan Mutar, you can keep the kids and the milk, okay,
there's no קדושה Kedusha in the kid and the milk, it's all
completely removed. Okay, לאחר פדיונן Leachar Pidyonan after it's been redeemed. Okay,
והשוחטן בחוץ פטור, Vehashochtan Bachutz Patur, if you שחט Shecht it now,
even if you have not yet redeemed it, if you שחט Shecht
it out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you do not transgress
for שחט-ing Shecht קרבנות Korbanos out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
because it never had קדושת קרבן. Kedushas Korban. Not only that, it
also has a מום, Mum, but we'll get to that later. But
anyway, this has never had קדושת קרבן, Kedushas Korban, therefore you can
שחט Shecht it out of the, you can't, but if you did
שחט Shecht it out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you do
not transgress for קרבנות Korbanos outside. ואין עושין תמורה, Veein Osin Temurah,
if you try to transfer the קדושה Kedusha of this to another
animal, okay, by a קרבן Korban if you do it, the other
animal you transgress, but and the other animal becomes a תמורה, Temurah,
gets the קדושה, Kedusha, the first and the first retains its status,
that's the מסכת Masechet of תמורה Temurah which we will learn. It
only applies to קרבנות, Korbanos, since this never had the קדושה Kedusha
of a קרבן, Korban, if you try to exchange it, it does
not affect, it does not transfer, it does not, the other animal
does not become קדוש, Kadosh, does not become a תמורה. Temurah. ואם
מתו, Veim Meisu, if it died before you redeemed it, יפדו, Yipadu,
you can redeem it even though it's dead. Why is that different
than a קרבן? Korban? Because a קרבן Korban we're going to see
there are two reasons you cannot redeem it once the animal has
died. Number one is the תורה Torah says והעמיד אותו הכהן והעריך
אותו לפני ה', Vehe'emid Oso Hakohen Vehe'erich Oso Lifnei Hashem, you stand
the animal up, and that applies by קרבנות, Korbanos, not by non-קרבנות,
Korbanos, although debatable, but that's what this משנה Mishna assumes, and therefore
if an animal is dead it cannot be redeemed if it's a
קרבן. Korban. And the other reason is is because there's a principle
that you do not redeem קרבנות Korbanos to turn them into dog
food. אין פודים את הקדשים להאכילן לכלבים. Ein Podin Es Hakodoshim Leha'achilan
Leklavim. So since this animal's going to be dog food, you haven't
שחט-ed Shecht it, it died naturally, so therefore if it was a
קרבן Korban you could not redeem it. But since it's not a
קרבן Korban and it was only going to go and it was
from the very outset it didn't have the קדושה, Kedusha, even after
it dies you can redeem. So that's an animal that started with.
...blemish, then you sanctified it, it never had the קדושה kedusha, *kedusha*
of a קרבן korban *korban*, therefore once it's removed it's fully removed
and even when it's there it's a different קדושה kedusha, *kedusha* than
the קדושה kedusha *kedusha* of a קרבן korban *korban* for like cases
of like when it dies or when you שחט *shecht* it outside
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*. חוץ *Chutz*, the exceptions to
this rule are מן הבכור ומן המעשר *min habechor umin hama'aser*. Firstborn
animals, another reason why this is in בכורות *Bechoros*, and מעשר maaser
*ma'aser*, the tenth. What do we say by there? There we say
that even if the animal that is firstborn has a blemish, okay,
it's born with a blemish, a permanent blemish or it's deformed or
whatever it is, because the Torah says by virtue of it being
born it has קדושת בכור bechor. *kedushas bechor*. And therefore the קדושה
kedusha *kedusha* of the בכור bechor *bechor* it wouldn't matter whether it
was firstborn and then got the blemish or had the blemish and
was then born, it is the same sense of the קדושה kedusha
*kedusha* of a קרבן korban *korban* with a blemish. Now actually the
interesting point here by a בכור bechor *bechor* is, is that what
the Torah actually says an interesting thing. Normally a קרבן korban *korban*
that has a blemish you have to redeem it and then bring
the use the money to buy a sacrifice. By a בכור bechor.
*bechor* what do you do with it if it has a blemish?
Anybody know? We haven't gotten to it yet. What do you do
if your בכור bechor, *bechor* has a blemish? You שחט *shecht* it
and you eat it outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*,
okay? The כהן kohen. *Kohen* still gets it, okay, it still has
קדושה kedusha *kedusha*, sort of residual קדושה kedusha? *kedusha*, a quasi-קדושה kedusha
*kedusha*, but it's not brought as a קרבן korban *korban*. So it
is interesting.
Does that mean you שחט *shecht* it and give the whole thing
to the כהן kohen. *Kohen*?
No, the כהן *Kohen* שחט *shechts* it, you give it to the
כהן *Kohen*, he שחט *shechts* it and eats it outside the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*. Okay, now anyway, so therefore but the
point being though that if it has a blemish, it is still
has this higher level of קדושה kedusha, *kedusha*, it's similar to an
animal that had was sanctified with with as a קרבן korban *korban*
got a blemish and then you redeem. So it's considered to be
the sanctity of a קרבן korban, *korban*, not at the full level,
you're not going to bring it, it's still it's still quasi or
residual, but it's still the sanctity of a קרבן korban. *korban* because
there it becomes sanctified by virtue of being born and it doesn't
matter where the when the blemish took place. Similarly by מעשר *ma'aser*,
okay, it's the Torah says the tenth one that you count of
your newly born animals when you're counting and giving the tenth one,
the tenth one is holy and it says regardless of whether it
has a blemish or not a blemish. So therefore in those two
cases by it's almost by virtue of a of a physical reality,
being born, being the tenth, being counted as the tenth, that gives
it the קדושה kedusha *kedusha* and therefore it has the same status
as if the blemish happened afterwards, okay? It does not and therefore
it has sort of like קרבן korban *korban* status with a blemish
as opposed to the first what we've been talking about which is
when the blemish preceded under normal cases the קדושה kedusha *kedusha* is
never even the קרבן korban *korban* קדושה kedusha...
*kedusha*. Can you call the ninth the tenth and the eleventh the
tenth, that too?
Yes, but oh you mean would that also for the blemish case?
I believe so, yes. Okay, so now that is the first cases,
so bracketing the exceptions, the basic rule is that it's not קדושת
קרבן kedushas korban *kedushas korban* if the blemish begin it comes first.
And now we go to the second cases. וכל שקדם הקדשן מומם
*V'chol shekodam hekdeshan mumam*,
let's say first you sanctified it and then it got a blemish.
Oh, מום mum עובר להקדשן *mum over l'hekdeshan*, it has transitory blemish
which doesn't really affect its identity or its status, ואחר כך *v'achar
mikach*, but just the point of mentioning that is don't think that
makes it different, ואחר כך *v'achar mikach* נולד להם מום mum, קבוע
*nold lahem mum kavua*, and then you sanctified it and then ואחר
כך *v'achar mikach* נולד להם מום mum? קבוע *nold lahem mum kavua*,
and then they got their permanent blemish. So the basic point is
a temporary blemish is irrelevant, but you first sanctified it then it
got their permanent blemish. So there the original sanctity was קרבן korban
*korban* sanctity, so even now with a blemish that sanctity does not
go away. ונפדו *V'nifdu*, and then it was redeemed, ופטורו מן הבכורה
ומן המתנות u'min hamatanos *u'pturu min habechora u'min hamatanos*. So now even
though you've redeemed it, since it started with קרבן korban, *korban sanctity*,
it has some residual קדושה kedusha *kedusha*. And therefore even after you've
redeemed it, if it has a firstborn animal, you are do not
give it as a firstborn. If you שחט *shecht* it, you don't
give the מתנות *matanos*, the זרוע לחיים וקיבה *zero'a lechayayim v'keiva* to
the כהן *Kohen* because even after it's been redeemed there's some residual
קדושה kedusha *kedusha* because it started with the קדושת קרבן kedushas korban.
*kedushas korban* and that really is clarified by the next line. ואינם
יוצאים לחולין *V'einam yotzim l'chullin*, they do not become fully desacralized, לגזוז
ולעבוד *ligzoz v'la'avod*, that they can be sheared or worked. Even after
you redeem a קרבן korban. *korban* with a blemish, you cannot shear
it, you cannot work it, which proves that it has some residual
קדושה kedushah. *kedusha*. And because of that residual קדושה kedushah *kedusha*, that's
why you don't have to give firstborn from it and you don't
have to give the מתנות *matanos*. ולדן וחלבן אסור אחר פדיונן *V'ladan
v'chalavan assur achar pidyonan*, even after you've redeemed it, if they give
birth or you milk them, then what they then that is forbidden.
We'll see the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will qualify, limit that rule, that
case about forbidding the milk and the children. והשוחטן בחוץ חייב chayiv
*V'hashochtan bachutz chayav*, if you שחט *shecht* them out of the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash* because they have the sanctity of a
קרבן korban *korban* you're חייב chayav, *chayav*. Now there's a problem here
that even though they have the sanctity of the קרבן korban. *korban*,
they have a blemish and you're not חייב chayav *chayav* for שחט
*shechting* outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash* unless it could
be brought in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*. Right? So
even if their קדושה kedushah *kedusha* is that of a קרבן korban
*korban*, how are you חייב *chayav*? And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
that we're talking here that it is such a subtle blemish, it's
like a cataract of the eye, that we would say that if
it were brought in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash* although
you're not allowed to, we would allow it to stay on the
altar. So in that type of a case you're חייב *chayav* if
you שחט *shecht* it outside. שחוטי חוץ *Shchutei chutz*. Because since in
theory if it were brought in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis
HaMikdash* בדיעבד b'di'eved? *bedi'eved* it would be allowed to stay on the
altar. Okay, so and the emphasis though here without getting into a
whole discussion about שחוטי חוץ *shchutei chutz*. And finally ועושים תמורה v'osim
tmura because it has קדושת קרבן kedushas korban... if you try to
exchange it with an animal, the other animal becomes a תמורה, tmura,
they both are sanctified. And ואם מתו v'im mesu if it died
before redemption, יקברו yikavru you cannot redeem it. Since it is a
קרבן korban it has to be alive to redeem it, and you
can't redeem it to feed to dog food, אין פודים קדשים להאכילן
לכלבים ein podin kodashim l'ha'achilan l'klavim and therefore you can't redeem. So
basically that's a lot of different הלכות and it's very hard to
absorb all that. Luckily the גמרא Gemara will go through them one
by one. But basically the upshot is that if you sanctify, if
it starts with a blemish and you sanctify it, it was never
קרבן korban sanctity and when you remove it there's nothing residual. If
it's you sanctify it and then it gets the blemish, it was
קרבן korban, sanctity and therefore even after you remove it there is
something residual that remains. Okay. ועושים תמורה v'osim tmura is before you
פודה. podeh. Yeah, ועושים תמורה temurah, is before it's redeemed. So now
let's take a look, now we can unpack this more slowly in
the גמרא. Gemara So let's take a look. ואם מתו v'im mesu
was even after it was redeemed? No, before. The whole point is
if it dies can you still redeem it. So let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara טעמא דנפדו taima d'nifdu הא לא נפדו
פטור מן הבכורה. ha lo nifdu patur min habechora. So first it
starts very simple. You had this animal with a blemish, you sanctified
it, you redeemed it, then you give firstborn. So it's only because
now it's been redeemed. But if you sanctified it and you haven't
redeemed it, even though the sanctity was not קרבן korban. sanctity because
it started with a blemish, you would be exempt from firstborn as
long as it had that sanctity. ומן המתנות and from giving the
gifts to the כהן. קסבר obviously the משנה Mishna. is of the
opinion קדושת דמים מדחה מן הבכורה ומן המתנות kedushas damim madcha min
habechora u'min hamatanos that sanctity just of value, not קרבן korban. sanctity,
pushes something away from the obligation of firstborn and from the gifts
to the כהן. Very simple point, see, we're taking it nice and
slow, nice and easy after that first משנה. Mishna So it says
the same thing. Look, the משנה Mishna. says that before you've redeemed
it, even though it started with a blemish, if you've redeemed it
then you give firstborn, but before you've redeemed it you don't. So
that just tells us this basic point that when something has קדושה,
kedushah even if it's not קרבן קדושה, korban kedushah. while it has
the קדושה kedushah it's exempt. So let's say for example I take
my my sheep here and I say explicitly, I know this I
can give this as a קרבן, korban actually we're going to have
that case in a minute, but let's say I say I am
only sanctifying it for the use of temple treasury, not for a
קרבן. korban. Now there's actually a question if I can do that.
Here's a better example.
Okay, let's say a donkey. Okay, because we have donkey possibility by
then. Okay, so I sanctify my donkey for הקדש, hekdesh, not as
a קרבן korban, obviously, for treasury. And then it gives birth to
an animal. So there, although it's clearly not
in the קרבן korban. world, it's only about treasury, since it still
is קדוש kadosh now, the firstborn is exempt from from the מצוה
mitzvah of פטר חמור. peter chamor. So that's the first point. That
yes, when you remove it, it's totally desacralized, you're חייב in בכור,
bechor but when it has the sanctity you're exempt even though it's
non-קרבן korban. sanctity, even though it's only קדושת דמים. kedushas damim. Okay,
very simple unpacking of that first line in the משנה. Mishna Okay,
so while it has the sanctity you're exempt. Now you've redeemed, now
you went ahead and you redeemed it, this thing that started with
a blemish, and it says you can do what you want, you
can shear it, you can work it, it has totally removed the
sanctity. ויוצא לחולין v'yotzei l'chullin
and it goes out to, you know, to be completely desacralized. טעמא
דנפדו. taima d'nifdu. The reason is you redeemed it. הא לא נפדו
אסור בגיזה ועבודה. ha lo nifdu assur b'giza v'avoda. So obviously again
the משנה Mishna implies that if you haven't yet redeemed it, you
cannot shear it and work it. Now let's ask ourselves why not?
It's not a קרבן, korban it doesn't have קדושת קרבן. kedushas korban
Now you can't keep the shearings, it's owned by the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash,
But let's say the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash wants to shear it,
right? Let's say you sanctify your sheep with a blemish, the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash, would like to make some profit off of it,
can they go ahead and start shearing it? So the משנה Mishnah
implies no, that it's forbidden in shearing until it's been redeemed. Once
it's redeemed, געזונטערהייט, gezunterheit, it's totally desacralized, but until then it's forbidden.
Now why is that true? That prohibition of shearing is only a
prohibition of קרבנות. korbanos. This does not have the sanctity of קרבנות.
korbanos. Let the בית המקדש shear it and make a profit. You
mean you shear it.
No, it doesn't say that.
It sounds like it's a strict prohibition. So the גמרא Gemara says
מסייע ליה לרבי אלעזר. mesayei lei l'Rabbi Elazar. This supports Rabbi Elazar
דאמר קדשי בדק הבית אסורים בגיזה ועבודה d'amar kodshei bedek habayis assurim
b'giza v'avoda that even things that are just sanctified for the treasury
cannot be shorn and worked, presumably because it looks too much similar
to things that are קרבנות. korbanos. Okay. Yes, of course, if I
donkey,
right, that would be presumably.
Right. Look, if I sanctify my car to the temple treasury, right,
they can start a taxi service as a way of, well actually
maybe that's an interesting question. Can they really? Can they really? I'm
not sure they really could do that because then somebody else is
using. But if they wanted to go ahead anyway and go ahead,
but the point is to haul cargo. Well, right, meaning right, the
point is you can't then anyway, I don't want to get into
that. We'll learn מסכת מעילה Masechet Meila when we get there. But
anyway, the point is why shouldn't they be allowed to shear it,
sell it? When they sell it, that act of selling removes the
קדושה kedushah from the shearings and let them make a profit. As
long as it's only owned by treasury and it's not a קרבן.
korban. By a קרבן korban the whole point is... it's all, it's
all הקדש hekdesh to the altar, you can't derail it even something,
you know, and you can't use it in any other way. But
by this, the whole point is for them to make money off
of it, so let them make money, they'll sell and they'll sell
the shearings. And the answer is, so but the משנה Mishnah applies
now and says this supports רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says not presumably because it looks too much like a קרבן.
korban So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say, it
doesn't exactly support רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Our case looks much more
like a קרבן korban. than another case. Why? Because our case, גמרא
Gemara says one minute, the גמרא says, אמרי לא, amri lo, it
doesn't exactly support רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. קדושת דמים למזבח הוא דמיחלפא
בקדושת הגוף למזבח גזרו בו רבנן. Kedushas damim l'mizbeach hu d'michlapa b'kedushas
haguf l'mizbeach gazru bo rabanan. Our case is, yes, it doesn't have
קרבן korban. sanctity, but you tried to give it קרבן korban sanctity.
You took this animal with a מום mum, and you said it's
an עולה. olah. So because it has a מום, mum that attempt
to make it a קרבן, korban that קדושה kedushah got transformed into
just monetary ownership of the temple. But it was an attempt to
give it קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf and again the point also there
is by the way that when you redeem it you're supposed to
use the proceeds to get a קרבן. korban. So even though it
is only קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, it's a קדושת דמים kedushas damim
that came through an attempt to give it a קדושה kedushah of
a קרבן. And therefore that can easily be confused with a real
קרבן and clearly on our משנה Mishnah. before you redeemed it we
do not want even we don't even want the temple to work
it or to shear it because it looks too much like a
קרבן. אבל קדשי בדק הבית לא, Aval kodshei bedek habayis lo, something
that was straight away sanctified for temple ownership, for temple treasury and
not for a קרבן, maybe that is not confused, will not be
confused and therefore we would maybe allow you to shear that and
work that. So we don't know, but you can't prove רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer from our משנה. Mishnah Mordechai you had a question? No.
Okay. Yes. Is it בדיעבד? b'di'eved, I mean, why would you, how
could you work it? How could you sanctify an animal that has
a מום? mum Oh yeah, yeah, you weren't aware, you didn't notice
the מום, or it's talking about בדיעבד, b'di'eved. you know, somehow you
thought, I don't know what was going through your head, you might
have been aware of it, but what is the effect of that
קדושה? kedushah We're going to have a whole מסכת Masechet that's about
בדיעבד. That's like the irony, there's an entire מסכת תמורה Masechet Temurah
which is all about the effects of doing an עבירה. aveira. Okay.
You're not allowed to do a תמורה, what happens if you do?
We have an entire מסכת Masechet about what happens if you did
it. Okay, so okay, so now so okay, so that second point.
Okay, so again it has קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, at least sometimes
this is framed as if you just want to get fully confused,
קדושת דמים למזבח. kedushas damim l'mizbeach. It's not קדושת מזבח kedushas mizbeach
in the sense that the קדושה kedushah, was never going to allow
this animal to get onto the altar, but it does have to
be sold and the proceeds do have to be used for a
קרבן. So it is somewhat between a little the two worlds and
that's why at least enough from an appearance perspective we don't let
you work it before you redeem it. Okay? So that's the first
two points. While it has קדושה, kedushah even קדושת דמים kedushas damim
you're exempt from בכורה, bechorah, while it has קדושה kedushah. don't work
it, why? At least that seems to be rabbinic because it really
could be maybe worked to
make a profit, but it looks too much like a קרבן. Yes.
You say while it has קדושה kedushah but I thought we said
it doesn't have... but it does have קדושה... kedushah, it doesn't have
קדושת קרבן... kedushat korban, this is a מום before you sanctify... yes,
but it doesn't have קדושת קרבן but it still has קדושת דמים
kedushas damim of its value. And that value still exempts it from
בכורה bechorah and still means don't work it at least because of
appearance sakes. Okay. ולדן וחלבן מותר. V'ladan v'chalavan mutar. Now, their children
and the milk even after you've redeemed it is מותר. mutar. Before
you've redeemed it is not. If it's, you
know, the הקדש hekdesh animal even if
it's owned by the temple treasury and it has kids or it
has milk, so that becomes הקדש hekdesh as well and the בית
המקדש can sell it and make a profit. But after you've redeemed
it you can benefit from the milk and the kids. Okay. Again
because it totally becomes desacralized. גמרא says היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's
the case? אילימא דעבר וילדה לאחר פדיונם, Ileima d'abir v'yaldah l'achar pidyonam,
after you redeemed them everything happened, it became pregnant and it gave
birth and because it's giving birth therefore it's also milking it, it's
milking because they've given birth. So all of this happened after you
redeemed it, פשיטא, pshita, of course you can benefit from it, חולין
נינהו, chullin inu, you've just said that after it's been redeemed
the whole thing is desacralized. So if everything happened after it's been
redeemed that's completely obvious. אלא דעבר לפני פדיונם וילדה לאחר פדיונם. Ela
d'abir lifnei pidyonam v'yaldah l'achar pidyonam. Oh here's the case. It became
pregnant before it was redeemed and then you redeemed it and then
it gave birth. So you might think that the fetus maybe has
some still קדושה kedushah. because it was it was you know it
was
pregnant with the fetus, the fetus was in the animal before it
was redeemed. So now of course it's of course the answer even
that is relatively obvious because if your redemption removes completely the קדושה
kedusha, from the mother it would presumably completely remove it from the
fetus as well but its
value is going to
be affected by that too. That is true too. So but anyway
it's not as obvious as when it all happened after the redemption.
So now the גמרא also wants to point out that what's also
it's implying is maybe not just that it's מותר mutar but it's
implying also the reverse, הא לפני פדיונם אסור. ha lifnei pidyonam assur.
Which means that let's say you haven't redeemed it at all and
then the animal became pregnant and gave birth and then started milking.
So what would be the status there? That sounds like that you
cannot benefit from it. So let's take a look, so let's now
the גמרא has the following question. Okay, so you have now we're
going to bracket the milk case for a minute. You have this
animal that was sanctified in a way that can never be brought
because it had a blemish. It got pregnant before you redeemed it
and given birth. So because it hasn't been redeemed, it's implicit in
the משנה mishna that those kids are not are not the חולין,
chullin, they have they get the sanctity of their mother, they have
קדושה. kedusha, Okay, and therefore now the question is but what do
you do with those kids? Because they got the קדושה kedusha, from
their mother. The mother's קדושה kedusha was never קרבן קדושה. kedusha, So
these kids cannot be brought as a קרבן even though they are
unblemished. Okay, just to show you about the sins of the parents
being visited on the children. These kids are unblemished, but because they
get their קדושה kedusha from the mother, they can't be brought as
a קרבן. So can you can you redeem them without a blemish?
Okay, normally you're never allowed to redeem a קרבן without a blemish.
This has קדושה which is you know this sort of middle road.
If it's just קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, no קרבן at all, then
of course you could redeem you could redeem your car that you
sanctified. But it's קדושת מזבח kedushat mizbe'ach that has been pushed away.
קדושה for the altar that has never been fit for the altar.
So therefore maybe because it's related to the world of קרבנות korbanot
it needs a blemish. On the other hand, since the קדושה never
will allow it to be brought, maybe it doesn't need a blemish
and you can redeem it without a blemish. So that's the question.
נפדים תמימים או אין נפדים תמימים? Nifdim temimim o ein nifdim temimim?
Can they be redeemed if they are unblemished or not? תא שמע,
Ta shema, come and hear. המקדיש בעלי מומים קבועים לגבי מזבח וילדו,
Hamakdish ba'alei mumim kevu'im legabei mizbe'ach veyaldu, somebody somebody מקדיש makdish
is a word that sometimes is used to mean you sanctify. Okay,
you sanctify blemished animals, fixed blemish, for the altar, and they gave
birth. ימכרו ואין צריכים מום. Yimachru ve'ein tzerichim mum. So here it's
an explicit teaching, okay? So it says sell them and they don't
need a blemish, and the act of sale is a way of
redeeming their value. שאין קדושה חלה עליהם, She'ein kedushah chalah aleihem,
that their sanctity they don't have now that doesn't mean they have
no sanctity, it means they don't have altar sanctity, they don't have
מזבח mizbe'ach sanctity. Why? ושלא יהא טפל חמור מן העיקר, Veshelo yehei
tafel chamur min ha'ikar,
because the derivative should not be more strict than the source, than
the foundation. So since their mother does not have קדושת מזבח, kedushat
mizbe'ach, they also do not have that קדושה and can be redeemed
without a blemish. So now the גמרא says, טעמא שלא יהא Ta'ama
shelo yehei now we're going to
so fine, you've answered that question. So the animal has this קדושה
but not heading for the altar. If it gives birth, the child
has the same קדושה, can be redeemed without a blemish. Okay, now
we're going to make yet another point. טעמא שלא יהא טפל חמור
מן העיקר. Ta'ama shelo yehei tafel chamur min ha'ikar. The point the
reason here that this kid is does not have קדושת מזבח kedushat
mizbe'ach is because it's limited by its mother, and the mother's קדושה
cannot bring is not headed for the altar. אבל, let's say you
had a similar case to giving birth to an unblemished kid, but
it was not limited by the mother. What would be the case?
Look at how it's look at the parallel it's drawing. הקדיש זכר
לדמיו. Hikdish zachar ledamav. Now it says זכר zachar male just because
normally you'd assume that people bringing קרבנות korbanot free will are bringing
עולות. olot. You can also bring a שלמים shelamim which is a
female, that's really not relevant. Let's take let's but it's assuming male
and an עולה. olah. So you have this beautiful sheep, unblemished, okay,
could be a male, could be a perfect עולה, olah, and you
say I am sanctifying this for the temple treasury. Okay, so now
it's the question about the reverse. We had that you were trying
to sanctify something for the altar, the physical reality prevented that and
transformed it into a treasury or a value sanctity. Let's say you
are trying to sanctify it for the treasury but the physical reality
allows this to to reach a higher purpose, not just be treated
as a piece of meat, but actually be brought as a קרבן.
Does it get an automatic upgrade? Okay, does that reality automatically transform
it to קדושת מזבח? kedushat mizbe'ach? So it's going to say הקדיש
זכר לדמיו קדוש קדושת הגוף. Hikdish zachar ledamav kadosh kedushat haguf.
It will become a קרבן. Why? How do we see this? By
the parallel or the contrast to the same type of perfect unblemished
male that's born to the mother with this with this limited קדושה.
That there we say what prevented the child from being a קרבן
was that the mother's קדושה was limited and it was limited by
the mother. But if you're not dealing with a mother's קדושה, you're
dealing with my verbal sanctification, there's nothing that limits it from being
upgraded and therefore it'll automatically upgrade. Okay, so therefore מסייע ליה לרבא,
Mesayei lei leRava, this supports רבא, Rava, דאמר רבא הקדיש זכר לדמים,
De'amar Rava hikdish zachar ledamim, you tried
to sanctify a perfect animal for its value, never קדוש קדושת הגוף,
kadosh kedushat haguf, it gets transferred and becomes the an actual intrinsic
קדושה. Okay, now one min now
I will say the following, one minute, that רש"י Rashi qualifies this
because again, remember that we're really dealing with three cases. One extreme
case is קדושת קרבן, the other extreme case is קדושת בדק הבית,
kedushat bedek habayit, something straight for the treasury. This is something where
you tried to make it a קרבן but it got derailed and
that's called קדושת דמים למזבח. kedushat damim lemizbe'ach. You have to sell
it but you use the money to bring
a
קרבן. Okay, so רש"י qualifies this. But what I said was, I
want to take this sheep, sell it, and use the proceeds to
go ahead and buy a קורבן. korban. Then it's like, why are
you doing such a convoluted thing? The thing itself should be the
קורבן. korban. So since in the end it's directed towards a קורבן,
korban, we shortcut, we do the shortcut and we make it the
קורבן korban itself. So רש״י Rashi reads that when it says קדושת
דמים Kedushat Damim here, it's the, it's this middle category that we've
been dealing with, and that's why it gets upgraded. So when that
happens to the sheep born from the mother, it gets, which is
the exact same קדושה, to be sold to be brought as a
קורבן, korban, it's limited by the mother and it doesn't get upgraded.
But when I do it directly and there is no mother, and
again it's to be sold as a קורבן, korban, then who needs
to sell it? And then it automatically does get upgraded. Okay, but
for the kids that are born to the mother, because they're limited,
you can redeem them even without a blemish.
Let's say it's a really like a nice big animal, I say
I want to bring two קורבנות, korbanot, then do we use the
same logic?
Presumably we do, because presumably the idea is better to, you know,
this thing is better that it should have, how could you trans,
this thing intrinsically is able to be done that. So, but yeah,
we'd have to see that סוגיא. sugia. Okay, קדוש קדושה, kadosh kedusha,
okay now, והשוחטן בחוץ פטור. v'hashochtan bachutz patur. If you slaughter them
outside the בית המקדש, you're exempt because A, it has a blemish,
and B, it does not have קדושה, an intrinsic קדושת קורבן. kedushat
korban. רבי אליעזר מתני חייב. Rabbi Eliezer matni chayav. Now רבי אליעזר's
Rabbi Eliezer ברייתא had a version of the משנה mishna, which says
חייב, which obviously doesn't fit the whole structure of the משנה, mishna,
which is to compare the cases in the beginning to the end.
But he says interestingly, not חייב for bringing it as a קורבן
korban outside the בית המקדש, that of course not, it's got a
blemish and it doesn't have that קדושה, but to tell you that
you are transgressing another thing. What do you transgress? ומוקמי לה בבמת
יחיד. umokmi lah b'vamat yachid. So it's your own, your own private
במה, bamah, okay, where and period where there was prior to the
בית המקדש where you were allowed to have your backyard במות, bamot,
okay, which is a pretty bizarre read of the משנה, mishna okay,
structurally clearly the משנה mishna is saying פטור. patur. Now also why
the משנה mishna. should be talking about a time when there's no
בית המקדש, but anyway he wanted to make his point. And his
point was that in a time when you're allowed to have private
במות bamot in your backyard and you bring a קורבן korban that's
a בעל מום, baal mum, do you transgress for bringing a בעל
מום baal mum קורבן korban on a private במה, bamah, or do
you only transgress when you bring it on in the בית המקדש
or on a central altar? דאמר רבי אליעזר מנין לזובח בהמה בעלת
מום בבמת יחיד בשעת היתר הבמות. D'amar Rabbi Eliezer minayin l'zoveiach behemah
baalat mum b'vamat yachid b'shaat heter habamot. How do you know if
somebody brings an animal with a מום on their private במה bamah
at the time when those are permitted, שהוא בלא תעשה, shehu b'lo
taaseh, you transgress, that they're not even allowed when they're private במות?
bamot? שנאמר לא תזבח לה׳ אלהיך שור ושה. Shene'emar lo tizbach l'Hashem
Elokecha shor va'seh. Do not slaughter to God an ox or a
sheep, כל דבר רע כי תועבת ה׳ אלהיך הוא, kol davar ra
ki toavat Hashem Elokecha hu, I think something like that. Anyway, so
do not bring a, don't bring to God an animal with a
blemish. אם אינו ענין לבמה גדולה, Im eino inyan l'bamah gedolah, you
don't need that for a central במה bamah like a בית המקדש,
דכתיב עור או שבור, d'chtiv iver o shavur, there's פסוקים psukim in
ויקרא Vayikra that list all of the blemishes that you can't bring
as a קורבן. korban. So why does it have to repeat it
in דברים? Devarim? I mean a lot of things are repeated in
דברים, Devarim, but why is this? תניהו ענין לבמת יחיד, Taneihu inyan
l'vamat yachid, that you can't even bring a blemished animal on a
private במה. bamah. So the גמרא says one minute, אימא, eima, why
don't I say אם אינו ענין לקדשים תניהו ענין לבכור? im eino
inyan l'kodshim taneihu inyan l'bechor? Maybe I should say that no, that
not only is there a problem with sacrifices having a blemish, but
even a בכור. Why would I think a בכור is different? It's
also sacrificed. Because remember, a בכור has its קדושה regardless of a
blemish, even if a blemish preceded it. So therefore maybe I would
be allowed to bring it even with its blemish. סלקא דעתך אמינא,
Salka daatach amina, I might have thought, הואיל ובקדוש כשהוא בעל מום,
ho b'kadosh k'shehu baal mum, since it gets full sanctity even with
a blemish, like a קורבן korban sanctity, ליקריב נמי כשהוא בעל מום,
likariv nami k'shehu baal mum, maybe I could bring it with a
blemish, and maybe the extra פסוק pasuk is coming to say that
blemishes are a problem with a בכור. קמשמע לן דלא, Kamashma lan
d'lo, and therefore it's telling me not, that it cannot be brought.
אמרי, Amri, no, you could say back, בכור בהדיא כתיב, bechor behedya
ktiv, it's explicit, פיסח או עור לא תזבחנו. piseiach o iver lo
tizbachenu. It says explicitly by a בכור, don't bring it with a
blemish. So you don't need it to learn it out from an
ambiguous פסוק. pasuk. It's explicit that you can't bring a בכור with
a blemish. ואימא אם אינו ענין לקדשים תניהו ענין למעשר? V'eima im
eino inyan l'kodshim taneihu inyan l'maaser? Okay, this is going to the
second exception mentioned in our משנה. mishna, Maybe it's telling me that
even an animal that's מעשר בהמה, maaser behemah, again remember that even
with a blemish gets full קדושה, maybe that animal as well, סלקא
דעתך אמינא, salka daatach amina, I might have thought, הואיל ובקדוש במומו,
ho b'kadosh b'mumo, since it's sanctified even with its blemish, דכתיב לא
יבקר בין טוב לרע ולא ימירנו, d'chtiv lo yivaker bein tov l'ra
v'lo y'mirennu, so since by the, by מעשר it says do not
do, the tenth one is קדוש kadosh regardless if it's good or
bad, and bad here means blemished,
and that's we thought about
that exception in our משנה, that even a blemished animal it has
the קדושת מעשר, kedushat maaser, the קדושה of a קורבן, korban, so
maybe I would think that because the blemished So since by the
by מעשר *Maaser* it says do not—the tenth one is קדוש *Kadosh*
regardless if it's good or bad, and bad here means blemished, and
that's—we thought about that exception in our משנה *Mishna*, that even a
blemished animal it has the קדושת מעשר *Kedushat Maaser*, the קדושה *Kedusha*
of a קרבן *Korban*. So maybe I would think that because the
blemish doesn't stand in the way for the קדושה *Kedusha*, maybe I
could bring it. נקרב נמי במומי *Nikariv nami bemumei*, bring it also
although it's blemished? קא משמע לן לא *Kamashmalan lo*, and therefore the
verse is telling me blemish is a problem even by מעשר *Maaser*.
So אמינא *Amina* no, מעשר נמי גמר העברה העברה מבכור *Maaser nami
gamar haavara haavara mibechor*, you make a גזירה שוה *Gezeira Shava* because
it says by—it says—it uses the word pass over, pass under the
rod and pass under by the בכור *Bechor*, and therefore the same
way בכור *Bechor* blemish cannot be brought, מעשר *Maaser* with a blemish
cannot be brought as well. You don't need an extra פסוק *Pasuk*
for that. So now the גמרא *Gemara* says אימא תנאיהו—אימא *Eima tanaiahu—eima*
why not say תנאיהו לתמורת קדשים *tanaiahu letmurat kodshim*, how about תמורה
*Tmura*? We're going through all the cases we mentioned in our משנה
*Mishna*. Why would I think you could bring a תמורה *Tmura* with
a blemish? דסלקא דעתך אמינא *Desalka daitach amina*, I would have thought
הוי קדושה כשהיא בעלת מום *Havei kedusha keshi baalat mum*, a תמורה
*Tmura* also is sanctified when it has a blemish, דכתיב לא יחליפנו
ולא ימיר אותו טוב ברע *Dechtiv lo yachlifenu velo yamir oto tov
bera*. It says you're not allowed to exchange one animal for another
with a קרבן *Korban*, make a תמורה *Tmura*, even if טוב *Tov*
again means unblemished, רע *Ra* means blemished, so even if the second
animal was blemished and you tried to transfer, that gets קדושה *Kedusha*
as well. So therefore as well you have a case where you
have קדושת קרבן *Kedushat Korban* irrespective of the blemish. Therefore maybe even
with a blemish it could be brought. So—so קרבה נמי כשהיא בעלת
מום *Kareva nami keshi baalat mum*, maybe you could also bring it?
קא משמע לן דלא *Kamashmalan dela*, it's telling you not. No, אמר
קרא *Amar kra*, והיה הוא ותמורתו יהיה קדש *Vehaya hu utmurato yihye
kodesh*, it and its exchange will be hekdesh. מה היא תמורתו כמותו
*Ma hi tmurato kemoto*, the תמורה *Tmura* is just like the original.
מה הוא במום לא *Ma hu bemum lo*, the same way the
original is not brought with a blemish, אף תמורתו במום לא *Af
tmurato bemum lo*, even the—even the exchange cannot be brought with a
blemish. So now what have we said? We have incidentally pointed out
that all these animals that had קדושה *Kedusha* irrespective of their blemish
preceding them, nevertheless you can't offer them up with a blemish and
we learned that out because of explicit פסוקים *Pesukim* or because of
links. So therefore that frees up the extra verse that says don't
bring an animal with a blemish for the teaching of—who was it?
רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* that says that even on a private altar
when those were permitted, even there blemished is a problem. So let's
just wrap this up. מתקיף לה רב זביד *Matkif la Rav Zevid*,
אימא תנאיהו לעולדות קדשים *Eima tanaiahu levladot kodshim*, maybe it's telling me
that—that don't bring a blemished animal when it's the child of an
animal that has a קרבן *Korban*. דסלקא דעתך אמינא *Desalka daitach amina*,
I would have thought הוי קדושתן כשהן בעלי מומין *Havei kedushatan keshen
baalei mumin*, אגב אמן *Agav iman*, since this is the reverse of
the case we had before. The mother is unblemished, the child is
born blemished, and the mother has קרבן *Korban* sanctity. So that קרבן
*Korban* sanctity applies to the child even though the blemish preceded because
it comes through the mother. So since it gets the sanctity irrespective
of their blemish, כשהן בעלי מומין נמי קרבי *Keshen baalei mumin nami
karevi*, maybe I can bring it on the altar even with a
blemish? קא משמע לן דלא *Kamashmalan dela*, and therefore it's telling you
not. So אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, no, פסקא תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל
*Paska tana devei Rabbi Yishmael*, we learned it from the teaching of
רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*. דתניא דבי רבי ישמעאל *Detanya devei Rabbi Yishmael*,
רק קדשיך אשר יהיו לך ונדריך *Rak kodshecha asher yihyu lecha unedarecha*,
only your sacrifices you should bring to the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*.
What is coming to include? We already know you bring sacrifices to
the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*. רק קדשיך *Rak kodshecha*, אלו התמורות *elu
hatmurot*. Number one to tell you that a תמורה *Tmura* קרבן *Korban*
animal you bring as a קרבן *Korban*. If you tried to exchange
them the קדושה *Kedusha* transfer—gets—attaches also to the second one, it can
be brought as a קרבן *Korban*. אשר יהיו לך *Asher yihyu lecha*,
אלו הולדות *elu havladot*. If the mother was sanctified and it gave
birth to a kid, so that child also has קדושת קרבן *Kedushat
Korban* and is brought assuming unblemished. Okay, so תמורה *Tmura* is brought,
a ולד *Vlad* is brought, ונדריך *unedarecha*, and like your—and your vows.
הקישן הכתוב לנדר *Hikishan hakatuv leneder*, they're just like a normal vowed
animal which means what? מה נדר במום לא *Ma neder bemum lo*,
the same way a normal animal that you sanctify cannot be brought
with a blemish, אף הני נמי במום לא *Af hani nami bemum
lo*. Here too also cannot. So basically just to wrap up what
we said is is that all these animals, it's actually a way
of going back to the משנה *Mishna* and emphasizing what are the
exceptions where you can have sanctity regardless or קרבן *Korban* sanctity I
should say regardless of the blemish. מעשר *Maaser*, בכור *Bechor*, and then
we've also mentioned תמורה *Tmura* because it transfers from the original regardless
of the blemish, and the child if it's born with a blemish
and the mother is a קרבן *Korban*, it has קדושת קרבן *Kedushat
Korban* again, not that it's actually brought, but it has קדושת קרבן
*Kedushat Korban*. All those cases because it has קדושת קרבן *Kedushat Korban*
even with the blemish, I might have thought that you can bring
it with a blemish, and there we have enough these פסוקים *Pesukim*
that say no, no, no, it has קדושה *Kedusha* and it can
be without a blemish it could be brought, with a blemish it
has that קדושה *Kedusha* yes, but it cannot be brought. And that
again allows רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* to say that there—that the פסוק
*Pasuk* about a blemish is coming to exclude even yet another case,
the case of your private במה *Bama*. Okay, so that's really not
so much our discussion, but it did allow us to again explore
this issue about exceptions to the case where it has a blemish
that precedes and nevertheless it has a קדושה *Kedusha* though it cannot
be brought. Okay, to be continued tomorrow. Who is it that the